Toldos, there he is, the 41st day in the Omer, שבועות Shavuos
is around the corner, and it is דף ג daf gimmel in
בבא קמא. Bava Kama. And we are dealing with the four categories
of נזיקין, nezikin, the גמרא Gemara under the rubric of asking the
question or under the whatever the framework of asking the question of
whether the תולדות, toldos, the subcategories, descendants of the אבות avos of
the major four categories mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, have the same
ruling or not the same ruling, is now going through all of
the אבות avos describing what is the parameters of those categories and
then telling us whether or not the thing other things that are
in the categories have the same laws or not, תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן
או לאו כיוצא בהן. toldosayhen k’yotsei bahen o lav k’yotsei bahen. So
we start with שור shor in the משנה Mishnah of which we
have a ברייתא beraisa that really subdivides שור shor into three other
אבות. avos. The משנה Mishnah does not call them תולדות. toldos. It
says there are three... the ברייתא beraisa says there are, you know,
three אבות avos within the שור, shor, and those are קרן, שן,
Keren, Shein, and רגל. regel. All right, we're going to have to
figure out which of those are included in the משנה Mishnah or
not. Anyway, so קרן, keren, the גמרא Gemara described as that's the
פרשה parshah in the Torah of goring where you pay half the
first three times and then the full. The גמרא Gemara describes it
as קרן, keren, using the horn, but quickly explains that what defines
that category is not the body part that is used, but the
nature of the act. And the nature of the act there is
כוונתו להזיק. kavanaso l’hazik. Its intention is to do damage. Okay, so
we'll maybe pick up from the bottom of דף ב עמוד ב
daf beis amud beis where the גמרא Gemara says the following,
אלא תולדותיהן לאו כיוצא בהן. ela toldosayhen lav k’yotsei bahen. It is
like eight lines from the bottom or seven lines from the bottom
starts from לאו כיוצא בהן. lav k’yotsei bahen. This statement that רב
פפא Rav Pappa says some of the תולדות toldos have the same
laws and some have different laws. So of course the default is
they have the same laws. The trick is to find the ones
that have different laws. So the idea that the תולדות toldos have
different laws, דאמר רב פפא אהיי. d’amar Rav Pappa a’hai. On which
of the categories of שור shor is it going on? אילימא אהני.
ileima a’hanei. So if it's going on the things we just mentioned,
קרן, keren, and the subcategories of קרן keren, is the same act
of כוונתו להזיק, kavanaso l’hazik, intending to do damage, except with different
body parts, by pushing, by kicking, by biting. Okay, so מאי שנא
קרן דכוונתו להזיק? mai shana keren d’kavanaso l’hazik? So how are there
laws different than קרן? keren קרן keren? is an intention to do
damage. וממונך ושמירתן עליך. u’mamoncha v’shmirasan alecha. It's your money and you
have an obligation to watch it and presumably and therefore you're חייב
chayav to pay. So הני נמי כוונתו להזיק וממונך ושמירתן עליך. hanei
nami kavanaso l’hazik u’mamoncha v’shmirasan alecha. These two: a, the way we
know that they fall into the category, what makes them a תולדה,
toldah, is the fact that they're כוונתו להזיק kavanaso l’hazik and they're
your ממון mamon and you have an obligation to watch them and
presumably what's missing is the punchline which is and they have the
same law that you're obligated to pay. So they're in the same
category,
they have the same characteristic, they have the same law. How is
it different? So the גמרא Gemara says you're right. תולדות דקרן כקרן.
toldos d’keren k’keren. Now I just want to stop for a second
because it is funny, right? The point of the גמרא Gemara should
be look, there you're חייב chayav to pay here you're חייב chayav
to pay and it's sort of missing the punchline. It describes what
makes it in the category but it doesn't identify the fact that
it has the same law. So it could be רש"י Rashi in
the later גמרא Gemara sort of puts that in and you're חייב
chayav to pay but it could also be, and this gets back
to our question of where to read the ו, vav, that no,
it is saying it has the same law because this gets back
to the question of whether וממונך ושמירתן עליך u’mamoncha v’shmirasan alecha is
a descriptor or that's actually telling you the consequence of being in
that category. Since it is כוונתו להזיק kavanaso l’hazik and you're ממונך,
mamoncha, therefore the law is you have an obligation to watch it,
right? And of course since you have an obligation to watch it
you're going to be חייב chayav to pay. But the first sort
of consequence of being in the category is not you're חייב chayav
to pay but שמירתן עליך. shmirasan alecha. All right, so it is
possible the גמרא Gemara is identifying also that they have the same
law. Anyway, the תולדות toldos of קרן keren follow the rule of
קרן. keren So that can't be the case that's לאו כיוצא בהן.
lav k’yotsei bahen. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, fine, you're right.
וכי קאמר רב פפא אשן ורגל. v’chi ka’amar Rav Pappa ashein v’regel.
So when רב פפא Rav Pappa says there are things that are
not like the... the תולדה toldah not like the אב, av, it's
talking about maybe it's talking about אשן ורגל. ashein v’regel. So now
let's talk about what are those categories of שן ורגל. shein v’regel.
So שן ורגל היכא כתיבא? shein v’regel heicha kesiva? Where are they
written? דתניא... d’tanya... meaning and what's the אב? av? Right? We want
to start where the presumption is what makes something the אב av
is the fact that it's the concrete case in the Torah. דתניא
d’tanya we taught in a ברייתא beraisa ושלח
את בעירו ובער בשדה אחר. v’shillach es be’iro u’vi’er bisdei acheir. Now
this is fascinating because there is a real interesting two ways of
reading these... these פסוקים. pesukim. The way the גמרא Gemara reads it
and the way that some Bible scholars read it, what they say
is the פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. So because it comes
right juxtaposed, the פסוקים pesukim that the גמרא Gemara reads about שן
ורגל shein v’regel never says שן ורגל shein v’regel and they are
juxtaposed with the פסוקים pesukim about אש. eish. So listen to the
פסוקים pesukim of the Torah here in משפטים, Mishpatim, okay. כי יבער
איש שדה או כרם ki ya’aveir ish sadeh o kherem ושלח את
בעירו ובער בשדה אחר מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. Veshilach et beiro
uvi'er bisdeh acher meitav sadehu umeitav karmo yeshaleim. Now what does that
sound like to you? Well, let's talk about the verb, כי יבער
איש. ki yaveer ish. So what does that sound like?
Made a fire, הבער.
hever. Okay, ושלח את בעירו, veshilach et beiro, so what does that...
what would that mean?
Basically to let it get out of control.
Well, or worse than that, ושלח veshilach is you intentionally, you made
with a fire, okay, כי יבער איש שדה או כרם, ki yaveer
ish sadeh o karem, right? It's not you're making a little fire
in your barbecue. You're, you're arsoning, you're burning a שדה או כרם,
sadeh o karem, you're burning down a field, and you're, and you're
sending it out, you're intentionally lighting something on fire, ובער בשדה אחר,
uvi'er bisdeh acher, or you could read it that you are, you
know, you, you made somehow a fire in your שדה וכרם, sadeh
vacharem, but then ושלח את בעירו, veshilach et beiro, you let it
out or you intentionally, actually wanted it to spread and it burnt
another field, מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. meitav sadehu umeitav karmo yeshaleim.
You have to pay the best. Now let's read the next פסוק,
pasuk, because the next פסוק pasuk is what the גמרא Gemara identifies
as אש. esh. כי תצא אש ומצאה קוצים ונאכל גדיש, Ki tetze
esh umatz'ah kotzim venachal gadish, so if a fire gets out and
eats, you know, thorns and just burns down a, what do you
call it, a haystack, a stack of wheat, not a haystack, או
הקמה o hakamah or standing wheat, או השדה, o hasadeh, שלם ישלם
המבעיר את הבערה. shalaim yeshaleim hamaveer et habe'irah. Then you have to
pay. So what's the difference if the first one was talking about
אש, esh, the second is also אש, esh, what's the difference?
The second was unintentional.
The second was unintentional, and what's the difference of the הלכה? halacha?
What?
The first one is מיטב שדהו, meitav sadehu, and the best of
your fields, you might have burnt down something that was only worth
a hundred dollars an acre, you have to pay a thousand dollars
an acre, because you were intentional burnt, it was an intentional act
of arson. Okay, whereas the second one was an accident, so it's
just you pay the, you pay the compensation. All right, that is
how, you know, biblical scholars, whatever, פשטנים, pashtanim, read those two פסוקים.
psukim. The גמרא Gemara does not read it that way. The second
פסוק pasuk is אש, esh, it doesn't... okay, how it's gonna deal
with intentional acts of arson we will get to, that might actually
be different, okay, we will get to that, but that's not what's
being talked about in the פסוקים. psukim. The second one is אש
esh and the first one is שן ורגל. shen v'regel. Okay, now
where do you get the idea of an animal going and chomping
on my neighbor's grass or wheat, or accidentally walking in the field
and trampling on some fruit? Where do you get that from כי
יבער איש ושלח את בעירו? ki yaveer ish veshilach et beiro? Somehow
בער ba'er to destroy, to consume, ושלח veshilach is going to... what?
הבערה. habe'irah. Right, so בערה, be'irah, thank you very much, can sometimes
mean animals, and we're going to now make see how the גמרא's
Gemara going to read this as שן ורגל. shen v'regel. Yes, Dov.
No, not Dov. Which one? Not the Rabbi Dov. Yes.
I was just wondering like, how... how do we really understand what
the word, the verb, ב-ז-ר, bet-zayin-resh, ב-ע-ר? bet-ayin-resh? It's burning, to consume,
right?
Right,
right, so that's exactly the key, going to be the key that
allows us to read it as consume rather than as burn. Yeah.
I also think that it's important that the verb is ושלח, veshilach,
causative, that there needed to be an agent that is to say
that the animal walked...
Right,
and the גמרא Gemara actually is going to have פסוקים psukim where
it speaks about, speaks about sending your animals. I don't know if
there're פסוקים psukim about sending your fire. Okay, it is interesting though
because we are going to read a ברייתא braita that speaks about
המשלח את הבערה ביד חרש שוטה וקטן. hamishaleiach et habe'irah beyad cheresh
shoteh vekatan. Okay, so it seems like that ברייתא braita is picking
up on the פשט peshat of these פסוקים. psukim. Okay, but the
גמרא Gemara here is going to say because בערה be'irah as Michael
says, it can refer to animals, can refer to consuming, ושלח veshilach
we have by animals, the גמרא Gemara therefore reads these פסוקים psukim
as שן ורגל. shen v'regel. Let's take a look. Okay.
So
וכי גמרה בבא שן ורגל. v'hechi gamra bava shen v'regel. שן ורגל
היכא כתיבי? shen v'regel heicha ktivi? Where are they written? Okay, so
it says the following. I just want to see one thing.
Yeah, you know, it's the whole way it introduces it, איכא מאן
דאמר דתנו רבנן, ika man de-amar d'tanu rabanan, כי יגח, ki yigach,
אין נגיחה אלא בקרן. ein negicha ela b'keren.
By שן ורגל shen v'regel it says שן ורגל היכא כתיבי? shen
v'regel heicha ktivi? Where are they written? Because you read the פסוק
pasuk and I don't see שן ורגל shen v'regel anywhere there. Okay,
so where are שן ורגל shen v'regel written? דתניא, d'tanya, we saw
in the ברייתא. braita. ושלח, veshilach, you will send forth, זה הרגל,
zeh haregel, that's trampling, וכן הוא אומר, vechein hu omer, thank you,
וכן הוא אומר משלחי רגל השור והחמור, vechein hu omer mishalchei regel
hashor vehachamor,
the one who sends the leg of the ox and the donkey.
Okay, so which is interesting also because the I, the owner, can
be intentional. I really am jealous of Michael, my fellow farmer here,
he had such a good yield. I am going to let my
animals out in his field so that they trample on his fruit.
That's my intention, that's ושלח את בעירו, veshilach et beiro, but the
animals, they're just walking. So that, right? So remember, קרן keren. is
כוונתו להזיק kavanato lehazik of the animal. The animal is intending to
damage. Here, I the owner could be trying to damage Michael's fruit,
but it's רגל regel because the animal's just walking. walking. As far
as the animal knows, it's just walking. Okay? So משלחי רגל השור
והחמור. meshallechei regel ha-shor ve-ha-chamor. וביער u-bi'er and consumes, so זה שן.
zeh Shen. That is the tooth, meaning it's just eating the food.
וכן אומר ve-chein omer כאשר יבער הגלל עד תמו. ka-asher yev'er ha-galal
ad tummo. So the whole question how to read this פסוק. pasuk.
רשי Rashi says it means the גלל galal רשי Rashi says is
the tooth, the tooth is sometimes like לגלות legalot is reveal, sometimes
it's hidden, sometimes it's covered, okay, consumes until it's done eating. Or
it could mean גלל galal could mean sort of excrement because it
eats and then it excretes. All right, anyway, it means it eats
to consume.
Well, you know the פסוק pasuk says משתין בקיר. mashtin bakir.
That's interesting. That's a good point. Okay.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, now, ושילח זו הרגל. v'shillach zo ha-Regel. וכן
אומר ve-chein omer משלחי רגל השור והחמור. meshallechei regel ha-shor ve-ha-chamor. No,
טעמא דכתב רחמנא ta'ama d'chsav rachmana משלחי רגל השור והחמור. meshallechei regel
ha-shor ve-ha-chamor. That's because it speaks about there's another פסוק pasuk that
says about sending out the leg, meaning and the trampling. הלאו
הכי במאי מוקמת לה? halav hachi be-mai mukmas lah? But anyway, of
course the פסוק pasuk has to mean שן shein, and רגל. Regel.
There's nothing else for it to mean.
Okay. אי קרן כתיב. ei Keren k'shiv. If it's about, I mean
of course this part of the פסוק pasuk has to mean רגל.
Regel. Because if it's about goring, we have an explicit פסוק. pasuk.
אי שן, i-Shen, if it's about eating, כתיב, k'shiv, that's the כי
יבער. ki yav'er. So of course ושילח v'shillach just by process of
elimination has to mean, you know, trampling. So the גמרא Gemara says
איצטריך. istrych. No, you need to explicitly learn out ושילח v'shillach means
trampling. סלקא דעתך אמינא salga daitach amina אידי ואידי אשן, idi ve-idi
a-Shen, I could have read the whole פרשה parsha talking about one
type of an act of consuming. So what's the difference about the
why do I need to say it twice? So it doesn't immediately
go to this issue about intentionally, it points to a different point.
חד דמכליה קרנא וחד דלא מכליה קרנא. had d'machlya karnah had d'lo
machlya karnah. Okay, one case would be that it destroys the principal,
meaning it completely destroys the object. Okay, that's the idea of וביער.
u-bi'er. ביער bi'er has a sense of complete destruction. And by and
the other part,
ושילח את בעירו, v'shillach es be-iro, maybe it's to tell me even
if it destroys it in a way that doesn't completely destroy it.
And it needs to tell me that you're חייב chayav in both
cases. So I would have said both of them are שן, Shen
but to describe cases of complete destruction and not complete destruction. I'll
get back in a minute to why it should have made a
difference.
Wait, Kozie uses the same word קרן keren with two different meanings.
What does it mean two different? קרנא karnah means. Oh, that's a
good point. I had I you know what? I so did not
even pick I so did not even pick up on that. That's
true. But you know, anyway, that's even in modern עברית. Hebrew. But
even in modern עברית, Hebrew, right, when you're paying back a mortgage,
you pay back
the קרן, keren right, exactly. Okay, fine. The קרן keren, is the
principal. Okay. חד דמכליה קרנא וחד דלא מכליה קרנא. had d'machlya karnah
had d'lo machlya karnah. קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you're חייב chayav
in both that that ושילח v'shillach means trampling and רגל, Regel, and
not just to cover both cases of destroying the principal and not
destroying the principal. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but now that
you said that that could there could be a difference, how do
you know both cases? והשתא דאוקמתה ארגל, ve-hashat d'ukemta a-Regel, now that
you're saying it's talking about רגל Regel ושילח, v'shillach, שן דלא מכליה
קרנא מנלן? Shen d'lo machlya karnah minalan? So now you've told me
ביער bi'er I would have limited to a consuming that destroys the
principal. So now where do I learn out a consuming and eating
that doesn't destroy the principal? So the גמרא Gemara says דומיא דרגל.
dumya d'Regel. No, you learn it because שן Shen, and רגל Regel
are right next to each other and in the same
פסוק. pasuk. מה רגל לא שנא מכליה קרנא ולא שנא לא מכליה
קרנא, mah Regel lo shna machlya karnah ve-lo shna lo machlya karnah,
by רגל Regel it doesn't have that phrase וביער. u-bi'er. ביער bi'er
points me to a sense of complete destruction. And I might have
limited it just to destroying the principal. But רגל Regel says ושילח
את בעירו. v'shillach et be-iro. That doesn't have a sense of ביער,
bi'er, complete destruction. So the same way רגל Regel is not limited
to cases of complete destroying and שן Shen appears right afterwards, I
know not to limit שן Shen to complete destroying. מה רגל לא
שנא מכליה קרנא ולא שנא לא מכליה קרנא, mah Regel lo shna
machlya karnah ve-lo shna lo machlya karnah, the same way by רגל
Regel it doesn't matter whether it is completely or not completely destroyed
because there's no word that would limit me to that. אף שן
לא שנא מכליה קרנא ולא שנא לא מכליה קרנא. af Shen lo
shna machlya karnah ve-lo shna lo machlya karnah. By שן Shen it
also does not matter. Okay, so anyway, by if it had just
said ביער, bi'er, I could have limited it to like full destroying,
because it comes together with רגל Regel I know not to limit
it to that. Now, one minute. What is the scenario of מכליה
קרנא? machlya karnah? So רשי Rashi says the scenario of מכליה קרנא
machlya karnah is or דלא מכליה קרנא, lo machlya karnah, not complete
destroying. So רשי Rashi says apparently if you eat the grain while
it is still like just beginning to grow, maybe, you know, it
hasn't ripened yet or whatever at a certain stage your animals can
graze on the grain and the grain it can graze on the
straw, the stalks or whatever it'll be, and it'll grow back. And
you'll still have, you know, your full yield of grain. So that
would be דלא מכליה קרנא lo machlya karnah because you're still going
to get your full yield of grain. Okay, now תוספות Tosafot says,
but I don't understand, it was מכליה קרנא machlya karnah if that
if we can assume that phenomenon, you know, I have no idea,
but if we can assume that phenomenon, they destroyed something of value
because I could have, you know, they destroyed the... the grain that
could be consumed and eaten that you know and that I could
have fed it to my animals and said this guy fed it
to his animals so it didn't destroy the grain you know that
a future was going to grow but there was some product here
of value that they fully destroyed right you get it they ate
they ate the straw let's say but that didn't affect the grain
and then the grain grew back fine but they destroyed the straw
that could I could have fed to my animals or I could
have sold to somebody else to feed to his animals so what's
לא מחייא קרנא lo mechaya karna so תוספות's Tosafos answer is that
לא מחייא קרנא lo mechaya karna basically means that like they got
it dirty let's say okay and I had to wash it and
rinse it so in that way there was a cost to me
to make it usable and sellable but they didn't actually destroy the
object alright so that's interesting right so that's really so then the
question is like that's even not so clear to me that's נזק
nezek if they like pooped on something let's say because later we're
going to have in a minute a version of שן Shen a
version of שן shein could be that they that
they pooped on something okay
so I guess you'd pay like how much no because that would
be גרמא grama that would exactly be the problem the question would
be how much would normal apples cost and how much would apples
with poop on them cost right because you could sell those apples
people are going to pay less but they could still use them
you just have to wash them up like you go to the
supermarket right and you know okay like I love these apples these
pink lady apples but they're exorbitantly expensive they're like three to five
dollars a pound I never buy them but
sometimes you go to the yeah sometimes you go to the like
you know the damaged produce section or sometimes they do this and
you get it for like 50 cents a pound all you gotta
do is just cut out the little piece that has the you
know that's a little brown spot and you get a 99 percent
worth of an apple for 50 cents right
generally it's disgusting but yeah once
in a okay anyway so the point is is that I got
it was worth a lot less than the two minutes of effort
it took me to fix it okay so the value actually goes
down the marketable value it's not the amount of effort to fix
it but it's לא מחייא קרנא lo mechaya karna in this case
if it had just been pooped on there's not even any physical
damage to the object itself okay so that's what תוספות Tosafos understands
as the לא מחייא קרנא lo mechaya karna yes Jake
so just to clarify like a tree like a fruit tree eating
the fruit on the fruit tree
is
מחייא קרנא mechaya karna right I might have thought I just to
clarify because I might have thought it isn't מחייא קרנא mechaya karna
no no no the
tree's still there
no no no according to רש״י Rashi you mean no no no
no no everybody would say that is מחייא קרנא mechaya karna you
totally destroyed the fruit and nothing is growing back right right רש״י
Rashi says לא מחייא קרנא lo mechaya karna is you ate the
straw but the grain is going to grow back but תוספות Tosafos
says okay but it's מחייא קרנא mechaya karna of the straw so
תוספות Tosafos has the לא מחייא
קרנא
lo
mechaya karna between רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos
between like the apple the apples all the fruit
because רש״י Rashi sees because right so that's תוספות's Tosafos question תוספות
Tosafos also doesn't see the difference but רש״י Rashi sees if you've
got a wheat field your produce here is the wheat and the
straw is incidental okay so some animal eats the straw but the
wheat is going to grow back from the perspective of the wheat
which is my yearly produce right nothing was destroyed the fact that
I could have made some money selling the straw at a certain
point and whatever that's not really affecting the wheat right but by
a tree the produce is the apples right so okay so anyway
yes
a question moving forward just picking up on a terminology in
the גמרא Gemara just this third line from the top there כמה
דכתב רחמנא ושלח וביער בשדה אחר kama de-chasav Rachmana ve-shillach u-vi'er be-sadeh
acheir does it usually say רחמנא Rachmana פסוק pasuk from נביאים Neviim
sometimes not usually but sometimes
what would it usually say
I don't know דכתיב de-chsiv or whatever okay alright yeah I understand
and before the גמרא Gemara challenged the question of are we learning
it from non from non תורה Torah from נביאים Neviim and דברי
קבלה Divrei Kabbalah okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
so now we got ושלח ve-shillach is רגל regel okay now אמר
מר וביער Amar Mar u-vi'er
now we're going to get שן shein it consumes זה השן zeh
ha-shein
that's the tooth וכן הוא אומר כאשר יער הגלל עד תמו ve-chein
hu omeir ka'asher yeva'er ha-galal ad tumo טעמא דכתב רחמנא כאשר יבער
הגלל tama de-chasav Rachmana ka'asher yeva'er ha-galal and as
Michael rightly says it's not רחמנא Rachmana exactly it's not the תורה
Torah but okay we have a פסוק pasuk that speaks about consuming
and somehow גלל galal tells us it means eating עד תמו ad
tumo הא לאו הכי במאי אוקימת ליה ha lav hachi be-mai ukmis
lei so the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute we could have
just figured that out by process of elimination what else could it
be talking about אי קרן כתיב ei keren kesiv קרן keren by
goring it says explicitly אי רגל כתיב ei regel kesiv because we
now established
ושלח את בעירו ve-shillach es be'iro is רגל regel so the גמרא
Gemara says אצטריך itztariich no no no you need to tell me
that that's talking about שן shein סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina
I would have thought אידי ואידי איהו רגל eidi ve-eidi ihu regel
they're both רגל regel חד דאזל ממילא וחד דשלח שלוחה chad de-azal
mimeila ve-chad de-shillach shiluchei
ah finally the גמרא Gemara is pointing to a real like issue
in the פסוק pasuk which is ושלח ve-shillach ושלח ve-shillach sounds intentional
so if it just said if I did not know וביער u-vi'er
was שן shein I would have said that actually the תורה Torah
is describing True forms of רגל Regel *regel*. ושלח את בעירה *ve-shilach
et be'iro*, I intentionally have my animal go trample Michael's fruit, and
ובער *u-vi'er*, no, they just on themselves walk into his field, but
I didn't send them. That's actually a very reasonable read of the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, right? ושלח *ve-shilach* really sounds like I intentionally did
it. Okay, so where was I? חד דשילח שלוחיה חד דאזלה ממילא
*had de-shilach shiluchei had de-azla mi-meila*. קא משמע לן *kamah mashmalan* that
the second part of the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* is talking about שן
shein *shein*. והשתא דאוקמיא אשן *ve-hashta de-ukmei a-shein*, now that the second
part is talking about שן Shen *shein*, רגל Regel. דאזלה ממילא מנלן
*regel de-azla mi-meila menalan*? How do you know if the animal just
walks on its own without the owner intentionally making it happen? דומיא
דשן *dumya de-shein*, by juxtaposition to the case of שן Shen *shein*.
מה שן Shen לא שנא שלח שלוחיה לא שנא אזלה ממילא *mah
shein lo shana shelach shiluchei lo shana azla mi-meila*, by שן Shen?
*shein* ובער *u-vi'er* you don't have the word ושלח *ve-shilach*, so שן
Shen *shein* you're חייב hayyav *chayav* whether it was sent or whether
it was doing it on its own, אף רגל Regel, לא שנא
שלח שלוחיה לא שנא אזלה ממילא *af regel lo shana shelach shiluchei
lo shana azla mi-meila*. So therefore by רגל Regel *regel* as well.
So now we've established ושלח את בעירה *ve-shilach et be'iro* means רגל
Regel? *regel*, ובער בשדה אחר *u-vi'er bi-sdei acher* means שן Shen *shein*,
although ושלח *ve-shilach* suggests intentional, intentionally doing it, the juxtaposition to שן
Shen *shein* tells us that doesn't matter, even with not intentionally doing
it, although ובער *u-vi'er* suggests מכלה יקרנה *makhaleh yakranah*, a full destruction,
the juxtaposition to רגל Regel. *regel* tells us that doesn't matter. So
don't read ושלח *ve-shilach* and ובער *u-vi'er* to limit the scope of
the nature of the action, that's not what they're about, it doesn't
matter those issues, and what they're really describing is the difference between
רגל Regel *regel* and שן Shen? *shein*. Yes.
It's starting to drive me a little crazy because it's
the exact same thing they could have said in a different דף
daf, *daf* like because the language is different here it must be
different. Right, except that because the language is different here but it's
next to the other word.
Right, although here they are, it's not just two separate פסוקים Pesukim
*pesukim*, they're ממש mamash *mamash* tightly bound in one פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
Like שן Shen *shein* and רגל Regel *regel* are usually spoken about
in like one breath, right? Not only because they're in the same
פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*, they have the exact same הלכות halachos. *halachot*, you
know? So there is that sense of they're tightly bound in one
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, they have the same הלכות *halachot*. But yes, if
what you're really saying is, do the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* probably have
a sense of what the הלכה halacha. *halacha* was and then working
it into the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, that is my sense in this
case. Yes.
Okay, so what is ושלח *ve-shilach* teaching then?
That's just a רגל Regel *regel*. ושלח *ve-shilach* is רגל Regel *regel*,
ובער *u-vi'er* is שן Shen
*shein*. But why use the word ושלח *ve-shilach*? Because that's a word
used by רגל Regel. *regel*, ושלח את בעירה *ve-shilach et be'iro*, okay,
I mean, or משלח רגל Regel. *meshallach regel*.
Okay, okay, so it's important to teach these two separate types of
damage with the exact same הלכות *halachot* so that someone doesn't come
to court and say for example what are you talking about that's
just what animals do.
Exactly, and that is by the way why they are the same
category, because that is just what animals do. Animals just walk and
eat. There's no intentionality of the animals to eat. Now again, part
of the חידוש chiddush. *chidush* is is that when I intentionally let
them loose so that they'll do what they naturally do, that does
not put it in a different category. My intention does not put
it in a different category, and that's why שן Shen. *shein* and
רגל Regel? *regel* are the same, because שן Shen. *shein* and רגל
Regel *regel* are not כוונתו להזיק *kavanato lehaziz*. They're doing their natural
things, it just so happened it was your food that got in
the way or your thing that got in the way.
Right, but yes, nonetheless I'm חייב hayyav *chayav*, I have a responsibility.
Exactly. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this. Okay, נכתוב
רחמנא ושלח ולא בעי ובער *niktov rachmana veshilach velo ba'ei u-vi'er*.
Now one minute, just say ושלח *ve-shilach* and don't say ובער *u-vi'er*,
and I could have figured out that the word ושלח *ve-shilach* could
have suggested both רגל Regel *regel* and שן Shen, *shein*.
Why? דמשמע רגל Regel?
ומשמע שן Shein. *de-mashma regel u-mashma shein*. משמע רגל Regel דכתיב משלח
רגל regel השור והחמור *mashma regel de-chtiv meshallach regel hashor ve-hachamor*, ומשמע
שן shen. *u-mashma shein*, where would you get שן shen, *shein* from
that? דכתיב ושן בהמות אשלח בם ashallach bam. *de-chtiv veshein behemot ashalach
bam*. Look at that! It even has the word ושן *veshein* in
it! How better can you be? And it's in the תורה *Torah*,
that's perfect! Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, אי לאו
קרא יתירה *ee lav kra yeteira* from ובער *u-vi'er*, הוה אמינא או
הא או הא o ha o ha, *hava amina o ha o
ha*. Then I would have had to figure, okay, the word ושלח
*ve-shilach* could mean one or the other, but I wouldn't have felt
entitled to read both. או רגל regel. *o regel*, now and now
it's going to make those points, which is what why might I
have thought one would be חייב chayav. *chayav* and not the other?
So here what we're getting to is the definition of the category,
which we said before by talking about קרן keren *keren*, and what
makes it why there's a basis for that to lead to the
sense that you should be חייב chayav *chayav*. The basic identity of
קרן Keren *keren* is כוונתו להזיק *kavanato lehaziz*, and of course you
understand why you should be חייב chayav *chayav*, it's an intentional act
of damage, even though not my intention, the animal's, but the fact
that it's seen as an act of היזק hezek *hezek*, an act
of היזק *hezek*, creates a greater sense of my responsibility to pay.
How about שן shen *shein* and רגל regel? *regel*? By the way,
the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I gotta tell you, this
is like I said yesterday, the way I just so love בבא
קמא *Bava Kamma*, you know, the פסוקים Pesukim *pesukim* are it's always
dealing with the פסוקים Pesukim, *pesukim* directly in conversation with the פסוקים
Pesukim *pesukim*. The פסוקים Pesukim *pesukim* are very concrete cases, like you
know an ox gores, splits the ox or whatever, and then what
the הלכה halacha. *halacha*... does is it abstracts it, says, okay, what's
the rule, let's move a step back from that exact concrete case,
right? So for example, when the תורה says if an ox gores,
splits the ox, doesn't mean split the ox, it means you pay
half the damages or whatever. You know, you pulled back and abstracted
it, right? So here the גמרא Gemara does that. קרן נגיחה Keren
Negichah means כוונה להזיק. kavanah lehazik. And it does it in these
like two words which precisely you know abstract it but in a
very precise way. So that it seems like you know that by
that there probably was a מסורה, mesorah, you know, wasn't something that
just the גמרא Gemara did. I think that for example the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi exactly uses the exact same words, right? So it's like there
was a clear,
precise abstract definition of these categories. So, קרן Keren was כוונה להזיק.
kavanah lehazik. What's שן ורגל? Shen veRegel? So it says like this,
it says,
okay, מכדי, Michdi, the גמרא Gemara says like this, או הא או
הא, one or the other. או רגל דהזיקה מצוי, o Regel dehezekah
matzuy, maybe I would have said it's just רגל regel, because animals
are always walking around and bumping into things. So the prevalence of
that would have explained why there's a greater responsibility. או שן דיש
הנאה להזיקה, o Shen deyesh hana'ah lehezekah, or
maybe only it's by eating because by eating the animal benefited. I
benefited from your fruit. How could I not pay you for what
my animal did? My animal now had a meal. Okay, and besides
that I benefited, the animal was more intentionally involved in the process.
The animal was knowingly eating your apples, okay? It wasn't knowingly bumping
into your, you know, bumping into your vase, but it was knowingly
eating your apples. So therefore I could have argued one or the
other, it's not necessarily true they're both the same, okay? So therefore
I needed the two, I needed just having the first half of
the פסוק pasuk, would not have been enough. So the גמרא Gemara,
says, one minute, מכדי שקולים הם ויבואו שניהם דהא מנא ומפקת. Michdi
shekulim heim veyavo'u sheneihem deha mana u'mapkat. The גמרא Gemara, says you're
right, you know what? It's true that each one has something unique
about it, but it's impossible to decide which is more important than
the other. If I tell you, okay, pick one that you're going
to be חייב chayav. for, שן shen. or רגל. regel. It's like,
I can't pick! Like there's both, there's a good reason to be
חייב chayav for both. There's different reasons, but they're of equal weight.
So when they're of equal weight and there's nothing that clearly sets
one apart to be the more weightier case, the גמרא Gemara said
what I would have done is I would have said both are
included in the פסוק. Pasuk And you have a פסוק Pasuk, for
both, משלחי רגל meshallechei regel and שן בהמות אשלח בם, shen behemot
ashallach bam, right? אשלח בם. So we still are back to our
question. ושילח את בעירו Veshillach et be'iro would have included both. Okay,
why did I need the second half of the פסוק? Pasuk So
the גמרא Gemara says, איצטריך. itztarich. No, you need it. סלקא דעתך
אמינא הני מילי היכא דשלח שלוחי. Salka da'atach amina hani millei heicha
deshallach shilluchei. Ah! If I just had ושילח את בעירו, veshillach et
be'iro, sure, ושילח את בעירו veshillach et be'iro would have given me
שן ורגל. Shen veRegel. משלחי רגל, meshallechei regel, שן בהמות אשלח בם,
shen behemot ashallach bam, but I wouldn't have known if they just
did it on their own. I would have limited it to when
I the owner intentionally set them, set them to do it, okay?
אבל אזלו ממילא לא. Aval azlu mimmeila lo. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan
וביער uvi'er that it's אזלו ממילא. azlu mimmeila. But now you have
an interesting question. I mean now it's just a hermeneutic question which
is, so what do you say פשט pshat of the פסוק Pasuk
is at the end? ושילח Veshillach means שן ורגל Shen veRegel cause
and actually now you understand why we're using the word שן shen.
because the פסוק Pasuk is שן בהמות אשלח בם. shen behemot ashallach
bam. If you asked me, there's no question that the מדרשי הלכה
midreshei halakha actually cause think of the words we use. We use
the word רגל, regel neither רגל regel, and שן appear in the
פסוק. But you know where you have רגל? regel משלחי רגל. meshallechei
regel. You know where you have שן? שן בהמות אשלח בם. So
I think in the מסקנא, maskana, it's actually ושילח את בעירו veshillach
et be'iro means שן ורגל Shen veRegel cause that word and וביער
בשדה אחר uvi'er bisdeh acher means even if it doesn't by itself,
even if you don't intentionally send it out, okay? So that actually,
right, maybe that makes Kahanja a little bit happier also, okay? Because
we actually are ממש putting both of them in the same word
of ושילח. veshillach. And וביער uvi'er is just telling you now that
we've established שן ורגל, Shen veRegel, it's even if they do it
on their own. And by the way, in the course of this
we've identified what makes those categories, אזלת, azlat, no, הזיקה מצוי hezekah
matzuy and הנאה להזיקה. hana'ah lehezekah. Yes, טוב. tov.
Yeah, I just want to, I want to push a little bit.
It's not clear to me that they should so absolutely be equal,
שן vs רגל. regel, I mean if my animal, something of mine
goes and just destroys stuff by walking all over it,
as opposed to getting הנאה hana'ah from it because it's been nourished.
Right, so you think
יש הנאה להזיקה yesh hana'ah lehezekah is, but you know, but here's
a different way of thinking about it by the way. I mean
we could always be bringing in, thing to always be thinking about
is which of the two models I laid out yesterday is the
operative model? Is it that I the owner am liable because I
was negligent through my object? Or is it that the animal did
an act of damage and since it's my animal I've got to
pay the same way I've got to pay for what my kids
do, I've got to pay for what my animals do. Okay, so
that actually very neatly falls out between שן ורגל. Shen veRegel. If
it's my negligence, I'm a lot more negligent by
רגל regel? because... negligence there, right? All it just has to do
is walk there, right? So הזיקא מצוי Hezeika matzui is a very
high level of responsibility, like is more, a very strong reason from
the perspective of the owner's negligence. But if it's an act that
my animal does I'm responsible for, well, an act that the animal
intentionally does and the animal is connected to in a deep way
and is being nourished by, makes more sense that that's the act.
If I start from the animal's act and not from my negligence,
so one act is like a sort of like, you know, מתעסק.
mit'asek. רגל regel, was מתעסק. mit'asek. It's not really the animal's act
so much, it accidentally bumped into something. שן is a real intentional
act. So actually they very neatly fall out between which model you
use of why I'm חייב. chayav, Greater negligence is, I mean if
it's negligence, רגל regel was greater negligence. If it's the animal's act,
we start with the act. If the animal did an act of
מזיק mazik that becomes my responsibility in שן is an act, רגל
regel is accidental and not really an act. Yes, and קרן Keren?
falls into both.
And קרן? Keren. Oh, קרן. Keren Well no, קרן Keren though, קרן
תם Keren tam is a very low level of negligence, but a
very high level of act of מזיק. mazik. Yeah,
though.
יש לומר וזה וזה. Yesh lomar vezeh vezeh. It feels like this
thing that that is more consequence to the owner of the animal
than to the one who got damaged. Because the one who got
damaged was like okay.
Right, exactly. Exactly.
But it's but the owner is like
oh I had this cow he...
Right, it also has to exactly. Okay, so let's take a look.
Now the גמרא, Gemara now that we've established that, let's look about
the צרי tzri whether the תולדות toldos are כיוצא keyotzei or לא
כיוצא lo keyotzei and repeat how we categorize the אב. av.
תולדות דשן מאי היא? Toldos de'Shen mai hee? What's the תולדה toldah
of שן? נתחככה בכותל להנאתה, Nitchakecha bekosel la'hana'asa, so we've described that
שן is הנאה להיזקא. hana'ah le'hezeika. The animal is out not trying
to hurt something and to do damage, but it's out to give
itself physical benefit.
Okay. So נתחככה בכותל להנאתה, Nitchakecha bekosel la'hana'asa, it rubbed up against
a wall to scratch itself and the wall let's say fell down.
Okay. וטינפה פירות להנאתה, Ve'tinfa peiros la'hana'asa, or it soiled fruit for
its own benefit. Now, presumably that means that it defecated on the
fruit, like תוספות Tosafot described before. Interestingly, because of a later גמרא,
Gemara
the later גמרא Gemara discusses an issue about what if it's not
the animal's body, actually we're going to get to it at the
end of today's דף, what if it's not the animal's body but
something that the animal projected, meaning like, you know, like the animal
kicked a rock and it broke something, right? So what would be
the case, a projectile? That's called צרורות. tzroros. What would be the
case about that or כוחו? kocho? It's not the body, it's the
something that the animal, you know, whatever, propelled by its body. So
anyway רש״י Rashi thinks that later that defecating is not the body
itself because it's actually the excrement that that damages the object, not
the body of the animal that damages the object.
Kicking a pebble, defecating, the same thing.
Exactly. So רש״י Rashi says טינפה פירות להנאתה tinfa peiros la'hana'asa would
be it rolled in the fruit in order like it rolled in
the grain in order because it like, you know, like like elephants
roll in mud, right? It rolled in the grain to get pleasure
from the act of rolling in it and that damaged it. So
that's a damaging with its body but it's an act being done
for the הנאה hana'ah of the animal. Yes.
What's the הנאה hana'ah of defecating? Relieving yourself. No on specifically on...
Oh right, so that's true. Another way you could also challenge the
reason of calling that שן is because although the animal is getting
pleasure, the the the pleasure is not connected to the damage. It's
sort of like it's sort of like the same incidental aspect of
the רגל. It's getting pleasure and incidentally there happened to have been
fruit there, but it's not pleasure derived from its interaction with the
fruit. Right, so that's another reason to say that it's not talking
about defecating. So רש״י Rashi says it's talking about rolling in the
fruit. And okay, so that's what רש״י Rashi says.
What?
An air freshener. The fruit is an air freshener for the animal.
That fragrance. It's not doing it for the perfume, it's doing it
for the physical pleasure.
That's how תוספות. Tosafot. Okay. Yes.
What? תוספות? Tosafot? I don't know. I mean that even if the
הנאה hana'ah is incidental. I mean even if the היזק is incidental
to the הנאה. hana'ah.
Chickens, chickens bathe in the dust.
I don't know why why you're such a חידוש. chiddush That's what
animals I mean, you know.
Chickens if they were defecating on the fruit that like they... They
like that.
They like that.
Oh, okay fine. I didn't know what you guys were talking about.
All right, moving on. All right. All right. I gotta work some
classroom management here. Moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says this.
Okay. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says that's שן. That's a תולדה
toldah of שן. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא שן דאיכא
הנאה להיזקא? Mai shena Shen de'ika hana'ah le'hezeika? So it's exactly the
same הלכה. halacha, שן, again here the conceptual definition, it gets benefit
through the act of damage and its intention is for benefit.
הנאה להיזקא. Hana'ah le'hezeika. וממונך ושמירתן עליך, U'mamonecha u'shmiratan alecha, it's your
property and you're obligated to watch it and you're חייב to pay.
Um, so הני נמי, hani nami, these two So the תולדות, toldos,
יש הנאה להיזקה yesh hana'ah lehizeika וממונך ושמירתן עליך, umamoncha u'shmiratan alecha,
so the תולדות toldos are כיוצא בהן. ki'otzei bahen. It's the same
category, it's הנאה להיזקה, hana'ah lehizeika, the same law. You have an
obligation to watch it, you're חייב to pay. Okay, so it's- so
that's in the- in רב פפא's Rav Pappa case of תולדות אי
לאו כיוצא בהן, Toldos ein lav ki'otzei bahen, that is כיוצא בהן.
ki'otzei bahen. אלא Ella
fine, that's not what רב פפא Rav Pappa was talking about. תולדה
דשן כשן. Tolda d'Shein k'Shein. All right, he's not talking about שן.
וכי קאמר רב פפא על תולדה דרגל? V'chi ka'amar Rav Pappa al
Tolda d'Regel? Maybe he's talking about רגל. All right, let's talk about
that. תולדה דרגל מאי? Tolda d'Regel mai? What's the תולדה? Toldah? Right,
notice how very beautifully structured the גמרא Gemara is, right? Here's the
פסוק, here's the אב, Av, right, now let's describe conceptually what the
category is and therefore what is the תולדה, Toldah, right, it's just
working through it all very nicely. Okay, so what's the תולדה Toldah
of the
רגל? הזיקה בגופה Heizika b'gufa דרך הלוכה, derech hilucha, it damages with
its body as it's walking.
בשערה B'sa'ara דרך הלוכה, derech hilucha, בשערה B'sa'ara presumably means its tail,
not a tear, okay, its- it swings its tail and that knocks
something over. בשליף הלב B'shlif ha'lev בפרומביא שבפיה, b'pumpyah she'b'piyah, or it
goes on the- the saddle or the bit in its mouth bumps
into something. So it doesn't have to be the body, it could
be something attached to the body. It's not a projectile, it's attached
to the body. בזוג שבצוארה B'zug she'b'tzavara or the bell. So anyway
it bumps into something. Okay, now by the way, it is interesting
because רש"י Rashi adds the words דרך הלוכה, derech hilucha, as it's
walking, and that repeated itself here, right, where it said- I mean
the גמרא Gemara, says דרך הלוכה, derech hilucha, anyway. So but רש"י
Rashi I think says it in describing, because רש"י's Rashi when he
describes רגל he doesn't just say, he doesn't just say הזיקא מצוי,
Heizika Matzui, it says הזיקא מצוי דרך הלוכה, Heizika Matzui derech hilucha,
he borrows that phrase in the גמרא, Gemara, right, 'cause it's not
anything that has prevalent damage, it's as it is walking. But I
want to just conceptualize it for a moment and say, it doesn't
actually have to be walking. Let's say an animal is standing still
and swinging its tail, right, or standing, you know, or I don't
know, let's say an animal is- you- I have my pet chimpanzee
or something and it's like- or whatever it is, animal's like reaching
for something, okay, what animals reach with their arms. Anyway, it doesn't
matter, okay, it's jumping up to try- it's not that it's walking,
it's- I think the more important point is that it's incidental. It's
going about its business, whatever its business is, and the damage occurs
incidentally, not intentionally, it's incidental but it's through the animal's normal going
about its business. So that's why you understand why that could be
described as הזיקא מצוי. Heizika Matzui. Animals are not walking themselves to
make sure they don't damage other people's property. So it's any type
of a thing that will happen in the normal course of the
animal going about its business, which could be a wide range of
things that will happen unintentionally, incidentally, in the normal course of the
animal going about its business. Okay, and that's what רגל is. What?
Why did you say that בשערה sa'ara is a tail? Is that
what רש"י Rashi means? נדבקו כלים בשערה וגררתן ושברתן? Nidbeku keilim b'sa'ara
v'graratan v'shivratan?
רש"י Rashi might literally say it means the hair, but I just-
that's- I think- I mean because- because to me to talk about
the hair catching- maybe, because it talks about physical objects on the
body like the- like the saddle, so maybe it's talking in stages.
The body, the hair, the saddle, but to me it's like- just
a- a more common scenario. How do your English translate it? Do
they say hair? Do they say- say tail? They say hair? How
do you say a tail of an animal? א זנב. A zanav.
Mmm.
Yeah, but what would- I don't understand what hair would mean.
Meaning it's- the hair caught- I mean I guess by a sheep
you could say, but then you wouldn't call it hair. I know,
I understand, that's why I- that's why I was inclined to translate
it as tail. Okay, let's move on.
Probably nothing because רש"י Rashi has to say something stuck to the
hair.
Right, exactly. All right, let's move on anyway. Okay, so מאי שנא
רגל דהזיקא מצוי? Mai shna Regel de'heizika matzui?
Notice how again though the גמרא Gemara drops the דרך הלוכה, derech
hilucha, because it's דרך הלוכה derech hilucha again doesn't mean as it's
walking, it means as it's going about its business. Okay, so how
is it different than רגל? רגל is the type of common damage,
like the, you know, it's- the- the likelihood of damage is prevalent
because it's just the things that happen as it's going about its
business. וממונך ושמירתן עליך, U'mamoncha u'shmiratan alecha, it's your property and you
have an obligation to watch it. So הני נמי, hanei nami, so
the תולדות Toldos have the same הלכה. halacha הזיקא מצוי וממונך ושמירתן
עליך. Heizika matzui u'mamoncha u'shmiratan alecha.
So that can't be what רב פפא's Rav Pappa talking about. Fine.
אלא תולדה דרגל כרגל, Ella tolda d'Regel k'Regel, fine, it has the
same הלכה, halacha, that's not what רב פפא Rav Pappa was talking
about. You're building up your anticipation, right? What is it that he's
talking about? וכי קאמר רב פפא א תולדה דבור, V'chi ka'amar Rav
Pappa a tolda d'Bor, okay, now we are going through the משנה,
Mishnah, right? The משנה Mishnah is שור, בור, מבעה, הבער, Shor, Bor,
Ma'aveh, Hev'er, okay, and we've now done שור Shor which is קרן,
keren, שן, right, שלש אבות נאמרו בשור, shalosh avos neemru b'shor, we
didn't call these תולדות. Toldos. If we called these תולדות, Toldos, by
the way, notice that we would have already had our answer, okay,
'cause these תולדות Toldos are not- I mean- well they're different, they're
not- right? קרן keren you pay half, these whatever, but we call
these separate אבות. Avos. So we've done the אבות Avos of the
שור, Shor, now we're up to בור. Bor. All right. וכי קאמר
רב פפא אבור, V'chi ka-amar Rav Pappa a-bor, a תולדה tolda of
the בור. Bor. תולדה דבור מאי ניהו? Tolda d'bor mai nihu? What's
a תולדה tolda of a בור? Bor? So, I mean, it's interesting
that it doesn't start by where is it written in the פסוקים
Pesukim because it's pretty implicit: כי יכרה איש בור או
כי יפתח איש בור ולא יכסנו ונפל שמה שור או חמור. Ki
yichreh ish bor o ki yiftach ish bor v'lo yichasenu v'nafal shama
shor o chamor. Okay. So because every of the other פסוקים Pesukim
need a little explication. By the נגיחה, negichah, you had to say
that meant
בקרן. b'keren. שן ורגל, Shen v'regel, you really had to prove. But
the גמרא Gemara doesn't even have to quote the פסוק by בור,
Bor, it's completely explicit. Okay, so it just jumps right into without
quoting the פסוק, what is the תולדה? tolda? Okay, so תולדה דבור
מאי
היא? Tolda d'bor mai hi? So מאי ניהו? mai nihu? אילימא אב
י ותולדה ט? Eileima av yud v'tolda tes? Maybe the אב av
is when it's עשרה טפחים asara tefachim deep and the תולדה tolda
is תשעה טפחים tisha tefachim deep. So the גמרא, Gemara now why
would that matter? Because the הלכה halacha is that the גמרא, Gemara
the הלכה, halacha not in the פסוקים, Pesukim but the הלכה halacha.
is that if it's עשרה טפחים asara tefachim deep, חז"ל Chazal understood
that it has the
normal propensity to cause death to an animal that would fall into
it. We're talking about three feet. I don't know, three feet seems
like not so deep to cause an animal to die, but okay.
Okay, anyway, but anything less than that, you could certainly understand חז"ל
Chazal saying that anything less than that, if an animal dies, it's
not your fault. Okay, if the animal you're only liable for an
animal's death, עשרה טפחים asara tefachim or deeper. Less than that, it's
not your fault. So that's the... but if it gets injured less
than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, you are liable. Okay, so that's how
חז"ל Chazal understand the difference between the depth of the בור. bor.
Generally breaking its leg, though, it's its demise.
Oh, you mean because then you're going to be forced to kill
it. Okay, but that's not the... okay.
Ah, so that might be. But that's interesting. I think הלכה halacha
would still say how much is an animal with a broken leg
worth? It might be worth zero, but that's not the case in
the פסוק where it says, you know, ונפל שמה שור, v'nafal shama
shor, I mean, it says והמת יהיה לו, v'hamet yihiyeh lo, the
פסוק is talking about a case of death. And what's more significant
is if it falls in less than עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and
it dies, if it falls in a three-foot-deep בור bor and dies,
they say that's some freak accident, that's not my fault. That's the
real point, that if it dies in less than עשרה טפחים, asara
tefachim, you're פטור. patur. Okay, so now, okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אילימא אב י ותולדה ט, Eileima av yud v'tolda
tes,
the אב av is עשרה טפחים asara tefachim and the תולדה tolda
is תשעה. tisha. Okay, now by the way, that actually would finally
be an answer of תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן toldoteihen k'yozei bahen because if
it's less than עשרה טפחים, asara tefachim, you're not liable for death.
Okay, we actually would have an answer.
Would that be considered a תולדה, tolda, though, ט? tes?
Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to sort of say. לא
ט כתיב ולא י כתיב. Lo tes ketiv v'lo yud ketiv. Why
are you going to call one an אב av and one a
תולדה? tolda? Neither of them are written. They're both the אב. av.
Okay, the גמרא Gemara, says no. הא לא קשיא, Ha lo kashya,
it has an answer to that. That wouldn't be difficult. והמת יהיה
לו אמר רחמנא, V'hamet yihiyeh lo amar Rachmana, the end of the
פסוק is, the dead you, the owner of the pit, keep the
corpse of the animal and you pay for the loss of its
value. Okay, so it's clear that the פשט pshat of the פסוקים
is that the animal died. Okay, so that makes the death בור
bor an אב av and the injury בור bor a תולדה. tolda.
And it's actually תולדה דלאו כיוצא בהן. tolda d'lav k'yozei bahen. So
the גמרא Gemara, says, וקמלו להו לרבנן י עבדי מיתה, v'kamlu lehu
l'rabanan yud avdi mitah, and the rabbis sort of assessed, evaluated, that
עשרה טפחים asara tefachim could cause death and you'd be liable. ט
נזיקין עבדי מיתה לא עבדי, Tes nezikin avdi mitah lo avdi, only
causes injury and not death and you wouldn't be liable. Okay, so
therefore we'd have the אב av and the תולדה tolda and it
would be לאו כיוצא בהן. lav k'yozei bahen. So the גמרא Gemara
does not want to end the conversation here because we got a
lot of the other אבות avos to go through. Okay, so we're
not going to accept that as an answer. So the גמרא Gemara
says, no, סוף סוף, sof sof, says the גמרא, Gemara זה אב
למיתה וזה אב לנזיקין. zeh av l'mitah v'zeh av l'nezikin. We're going
to refuse to call it a תולדה tolda because since at the
end, it's like you've stacked the deck that you're not going to
now have a תולדותיהן לאו כיוצא בהן toldoteihen lav k'yozei bahen because
you get to call it a separate אב. av. Okay, so there's
an אב, av, a type of a בור bor that causes death,
and then there's something which is not a תולדה, tolda, it's a
different type of a בור bor and it's an אב, av, an
אב av that causes נזק. nezek. All right. Now, by the way,
it's interesting, I should say by שבת, Shabbat, according to some ראשונים,
Rishonim, you have this. You have by שבת Shabbat an idea of
something called like a parallel אב, av, like is בישול ואפיה bishul
v'afiyah is, like, is אפיה afiyah the אב av and בישול bishul
the תולדה, tolda, or those really like parallel אבות? avos? Okay, so
you have the same idea here. Okay, so they're both אבות. avos.
All right, אלא, ela, the גמרא, Gemara now רש"י Rashi says, רש"י
Rashi says maybe because since the פסוקים themselves is unclear, even though
we say the end of the פסוקים is talking about death, the
beginning of the פסוקים clearly is talking about both. So at the
end of the day, we don't get to label one an אב
av and one a תולדה tolda since the פסוקים are pretty general,
we're going to call them both parallel אבות avos and we're not
going to have a case of לאו כיוצא בהן lav k'yozei bahen
just by virtue of that. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so
what would a תולדה tolda be then? אלא, ela, here's a תולדה.
tolda. אבנו סכינו ומשאו שהניחן ברשות הרבים, Avno sakino umaso shehinichan b'reshut
harabbim,
a public hazard. This is like the פסוק *pasuk* about the literalness
of the פסוק *pasuk* of לפני עיוור לא תתן מכשול *lifnei iver
lo titein michshol*. I leave a stone in the middle of the
road, okay, or my knife, or
my knapsack, my burden. And some animal or person trips on it
and gets damaged. That's a תולדה toldah? *toldah* of בור bor, *bor*.
It's a hazard in the middle of the street that somebody is
going to come to. It's not going to go out and damage,
but somebody is going to come to it and it's going to
cause the person that walks on them, in them, over them, to
be hurt, to trip over them and to be hurt. Okay, and
that's a תולדה toldah. *toldah*. שהניחן ברשות הרבים *sheh-hiniyacham bireshut harabim*, you
left it in the middle of the street. היכי דמי heichi dami?
*heichi dami*? תזא זיקא ואיכא *taza zika ve-ika* damage. What's the case?
היכי דמי heichi dami? *heichi dami*? אי דאפקרינהו *iy de-afkerinhu*, if you
made it הפקר hefker. *hefker*, you gave up your ownership of your
burden or of your rock or whatever it was, בין לרב בין
לשמואל היינו בור bein l'Rav bein l'Shmuel hainu bor. *bein lerav bein
lishmuel hainu bor*. So then it would be בור bor *bor*, which
is not saying it's not a תולדה toldah. *toldah*, it's saying great,
that would be a perfect example of a תולדה toldah, *toldah* of
בור bor. *bor*. Why
we're going to see why you have to be מפקיר *mafkir* it,
why that's relevant in a minute. But you have a hazard in
the middle of רשות הרבים reshus harabim, *reshut harabim*, okay, which you
don't own. That's exactly like a בור bor. *bor*. You don't own
a well that you dug in the middle of the street. You
don't own it. It's a hazard. People come to it and trip
on it. It doesn't go out and damage somebody. That is a
תולדה toldah. *toldah* of בור bor. *bor*. Great, we've got the תולדה
toldah, *toldah*. But it's not what רב Rav פפא *Rav Pappa* is
talking about because it's כיוצא בהם *ke-yotzei bahem*, okay? ואי דלא אפקרינהו
*ve-iy delo afkerinhu*, now let's say you weren't מפקיר *mafkir* it, okay.
Now it's an interesting debate of רב Rav, ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. Because
why is it a debate? אי ושמואל דאמר כולם מבור למדנו *iy
u-Shmuel damar kulam mibor lamadnu*, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* would say even that
case we learn from בור *bor* and that's a case of a
בור *bor*. היינו בור *hainu bor*, so it's כיוצא בהם *ke-yotzei bahem*.
It's a תולדה toldah. *toldah* but with the same הלכות *halachot*. אי
לרב דאמר כולם משור למדנו *iy lerav de'amar kulam mishor lamadnu*, now
רב *Rav* would actually say that's a שור shor *shor*. Now this
is going to get fun. Because later in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*,
not yet, we're obviously
giving a foretaste
for it, we're going now after we define the categories, we get
to figure out well what type of interesting things that are hybrids,
which category do they fall into. Right. Yeah. So if I've got
something that is my property,
classic בור *bor* has the following characteristics: It's in the middle of
the street, it's a hazard that something comes to, it does not
go out and damage, and it's something that I don't own.
Classic שור shor. *shor*, right, if sort of we just for a
minute generalize all of them together for a moment, although we could
speak about one of them, is an object that I own, okay,
right, ממונך *mamoncha*,
whatever. Fire I don't own it in the same way. שור shor
*shor* is like a physical stable object that's my property. I could
make you pay if you stole it. It's not like my fire.
So שור shor *shor* is very heavily ממונך *mamoncha*, my property. On
the other hand, it goes out and damages. Okay, so what do
you do about something that's in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* and a
hazard but I own it? It's a physical piece of property that
I own. Is that my שור shor *shor* or is that my
בור *bor*? I mean, I don't know, I don't want to speak
for you, but to me it seems pretty obvious it should be
בור *bor*. Okay, but anyway, but the גמרא *Gemara* has a debate
of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. Alright. So שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel* says it's
a בור *bor*, ואי לרב דאמר כולם משור למדנו *ve-iy lerav damar
kulam mishor lamadnu*, now רב *Rav* says it's a שור *shor*. That
you own it, and it's the physical piece of property you own,
for him that's the most significant to put it in the שור
*shor* category. היינו שור *hainu shor*. So and the point being, okay,
so however you categorize it, it's תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן toldosaihen k'yotzei bahen.
*toldoseihen ke-yotzei bahem*. It's an interesting hybrid case. It might be שור
*shor*, it might be בור *bor*, but it's still תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן
toldosaihen k'yotzei bahen. *toldoseihen ke-yotzei bahem*. Yes, Jenna, what's your question?
Another important difference is, assuming the בור *bor*, you could take it
out of the middle of the road.
Oh, that's a good point. The בור *bor* you could close up,
but essentially by closing up you stop it from being a בור
*bor*. Right. So this actually is not permanently in there, that's a
nice other point. Right. So there you go. So you got this
nice debate of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*, but either way it's תולדותיהן
כיוצא בהן toldosaihen k'yotzei bahen. *toldoseihen ke-yotzei bahem*. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, מאי שנא בור שכן תחלת עשייתו לנזק *mai shna bor she-kein
techilat asiyato lenezek*? And now the גמרא *Gemara* uses the phrase, we're
going to abstract it and point out what the law is. תחלת
עשייתו לנזק *techilat asiyato lenezek*. Now that's interesting, right? If you asked
me to be very contemporary, if you asked me, I would have
emphasized what I said before, which is that it doesn't go out
and damage, somebody comes and falls in it, trips over it, it
causes somebody or some animal, whatever, to injure themselves because it's... but
the גמרא *Gemara* is emphasizing, yes, but because it's a public hazard.
Before we talk about whether it's going out or something is coming
to it, the first problem you identify with this is this is
a hazard. What this is, this is going to damage. Somebody is
going to get hurt. Okay, and that's very different, you know, an
ox starts its life and the primary way when you look at
an ox you don't say, oh my god, public hazard, right? That's
not its basic identity and it's not the way it starts its
life, right? But then, you know, certainly when it was born it
wasn't yet had a propensity to damage or to do any type
of thing. A fire maybe is a little bit different because you
really see the potential for damage by the fire. Okay, but nevertheless
this thing, its immediate identity when it comes into being is this
is... you cannot put that here. That is a hazard, okay? So
that is the basic identity of the בור, okay? תחילת עשייתו לנזק.
techilas asiyaso l'nezek. Okay, וממונו ושמירתו עליך. u'mamono v'shmiraso alecha. It's your
money and you're liable for it, and this would be the same.
Okay, so הני נמי תחילת עשייתו לנזק וממונא ושמירתו עליך. hanei nami
techilas asiyaso l'nezek u'mamona u'shmiraso alecha.
Well, in the רשות הרבים, it's a good point. But you know,
in its current placement, once it gets the identity of בור, it's
תחילת עשייתו לנזק, techilas asiyaso l'nezek, which might be a little bit
of a tautology. Okay, fine. אלא תולדה דבור כבור. ella toldah d'bor
k'bor. Fine, that's כיוצא בהן. k'yotzei bahen. וכי קאמר רב
פפא אטולדה דמבעה, v'chi ka'amar Rav Pappa a'toldah d'mav'eh, moving down the
list, שור בור up to מבעה. mav'eh.
Well, it's going to have to be heather then, right?
No, this we're going to give an excuse to go through the
whole list, and then we're going to go back and tell you
what the answer is. Okay, so וכי קאמר רב פפא אטולדה דמבעה.
v'chi ka'amar Rav Pappa a'toldah d'mav'eh. מאי ניהו? mai nihu? Now, what
is מבעה? mav'eh? What does that word mean? We're finally going to
get to what the debate, I mean, we're going to refer to
the debate, we're going to get to it, focus on it later.
מאי ניהו? mai nihu? אי לשמואל דאמר מבעה זו שן. ei l'Shmuel
d'amar mav'eh zo shen. He says מבעה mav'eh is שן. Okay, because
remember, the משנה mishnah says שור. It didn't tell which of the
שורs. So שמואל says מבעה mav'eh is שן, which makes שור the
קרן, keren, because שן and רגל sort of go together. Okay, so
for שמואל, שור is קרן keren and מבעה mav'eh is שן ורגל.
shen v'regel. Okay, אי לשמואל ei l'Shmuel but really the גמרא's going
to say שן. דאמר מבעה זו
שן, d'amar mav'eh zo shen, אוקימנא תולדה דשן כשן. okimna toldah d'shen
k'shen. So we already covered that. תולדה דשן toldah d'shen is like
שן. אי לרב דאמר מבעה זה אדם. ei l'Rav d'amar mav'eh zeh
adam. Ah, now רב says מבעה mav'eh is אדם המזיק. adam hamazik.
That's funny, because that's like putting what does it mean conceptually for
your damage in the same category as your money's damage? Okay, so
anyway, so let's take a look at אבות ותולדות avos v'toldos by
אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. מאי אבות ומאי תולדות אית ביה? mai avos
u'mai toldos is beih? Okay, what's an אב av and what's a
תולדה? toldah You damage something... וכי תימא אב ער ותולדה ישן. v'chi
teima av eir v'toldah yashen.
So maybe when you're awake, that's the אב, av, because normally somebody
does damage when they're awake. When they do damage in their sleep,
that's a תולדה. toldah Also, to what degree are you also like
the same person, you know, the same person when you're sleeping? Sometimes
it's unintentional. You're like not conscious. Like, you're not an agent sort
of. So maybe that's a תולדה. toldah Now, והתנן, v'hatnan, but we
okay, but it is כיוצא בהן. k'yotzei bahen. אדם מועד לעולם, adam
mu'ad l'olam, a person is always a מועד, mu'ad, בין ער בין
ישן, bein eir bein yashen, whether awake, whether asleep.
So תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן. toldosaihen k'yotzei bahen. Okay, if you do damage
in your sleep, you are חייב. אלא אכיחו וניעו. ella a'keicho v'ni'o.
Maybe it's about your spit and your phlegm, or your what's it
called from the nose? Mucus. Your mucus. היכי דמי?
אי בהדי דאזלי קמזקי. ei bahadi d'azlei k'mazkei. Let's say you spit
and as the spit is traveling, it damages something. רש"י Rashi says
it hits some beautiful silk and it gives water damage to the
silk. כוחו הוא. kocho hu. So that's your energy, your projectile. And
something that is your כוח, koach, even if it's not your physical
body, but something that you threw and has your energy in it
that's propelling it, that's the idea of כוח, koach, it's your energy
that's propelling it. That's like your body did it. Okay, and then,
so then fine, that might be a תולדה, tolada, but we would
be back to the point of תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן. keyotzei bahen. We're
not debating that you're חייב in these cases, that that is a
תולדה. tolada, Maybe a sleep is a תולדה, tolada maybe your כוח
koach is a תולדה. tolada All of those are certainly at one
degree removed from the classic case of you being an awake agent
damaging something with your body. But still, it's תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן. keyotzei
bahen. Okay, so אי בתר דנייח. ei basar d'nayach. Now let's say
you spat and it fell on the ground and some animal came
and slipped on it. Okay, so that's maybe a different הלכה. halacha
But what type of category? What would you put that into? Let
me ask you, quick. בור. Thank you, right? So בין לרב בין
לשמואל היינו בור. You don't want to say, wait, wait, it's still
my spit, I still own it. Okay, that's clearly a case of
הפקר. Okay, so that's a בור. So we've already established תולדה דבור
toldah d'bor is like a בור. So even if we have, so
conceptually it's interesting, what is a תולדה tolada of an אדם המזיק?
adam hamazik? Is it when you're asleep? Is it your כוח? koach?
One is more, right? There are different ways in which that's less
like you. But either way, it's תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן. So that's not
going to work.
How are we translating מבעה? mav'eh?
According to רב, it means אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. We'll get to
that in a minute, why it means אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. אלא.
ella. Okay, so the גמרא says one minute, אלא תולדה דמבעה כמבעה.
ella toldah d'mav'eh k'mav'eh. Fine, the תולדה of מבעה mav'eh is like
מבעה. mav'eh. וכי קאמר רב פפא אטולדה דאש. v'chi ka'amar Rav Pappa
a'toldah d'eish. So we're going to do heather. I know it's 8:30,
but let's just give it like three more minutes.
So תולדה דאש מאי ניהו? toldah d'eish mai nihu? What's a
תולדה of אש? eish? אילימא אבנו וסכינו ומשאו שהניחן בראש גגו. eileima
avno v'sakino u'masa'o she'henichan b'rosh gago. Let's say I took that same
stone, knife, and burden, but I didn't put it in the middle
of the street. I put it on the top of my roof.
And what happened? A wind came and blew it off the roof
and hit somebody as it was falling down. That would be a
type of an אש esh cause I make it in my field,
some other strength comes, the wind comes and causes it to spread.
It's not exactly אש, esh, here the gravity is causing damage by
the אש, esh, it's the, you know, consuming power of the fire
that's causing the damage. But nevertheless, it's moving, something else, you know,
caused, propelled it, okay, and that would be a type of an
אש. esh. So that's interesting.
I don't know if I would call it...
No, that's because that's my direct... my energy. This is I put
it down, my energy stopped and some other energy caused it to
move. Okay, ונפלו ברוח מצויה, venafelu beruach metzuya, and they fell with
an expected wind. If it's an uncommon wind, it's not my fault,
but it's a type of wind that I could have expected. והזיקו,
vehiziku, and they damaged. היכי דמי? אי בהדי דאזלי קמזקו, ei behadei
de'azli kamaziku, if they were damaging as they were falling or moving,
okay, היינו אש. hainu esh. So okay, you're חייב, it is אש,
esh, it is a תולדה, but it's כיוצא בהן. מאי שנא אש
דכוח אחר מעורב בהן? mai shena esh dekoach acher me'urav bahen? Now
that's a fascinating definition of אש. esh. I don't know if I
would have said that is the primary characteristic of אש, esh, but
here's how the גמרא is saying it. Some other... some other
energy gets mixed up in them. Alright, something comes and causes it
to spread. Okay, so that's the אש. esh. I might, you know,
maybe you want to, I would add to it the fact that
you could have anticipated it and there was a likelihood that it
would have caused damage if something would have come and it would
have spread. Okay, by the way, why is אש esh always about
wind? Right?
I mean, why is it out about wind? That's also about fuel.
In other words, maybe we normally tend to read that as about
wind. And if there's no wind and I have a fire in
my yard, will it spread?
If it's consuming... if there's... if there's fuel, it will spread. Right.
But if it's, let's say you have... it's a candle.
Right, if it's contained it won't. So it is interesting though that
it describes it as כוח אחר מעורב. koach acher me'urav. You could
say כוח אחר koach acher tends to be read as wind, but
you're right, you could say it's the natural consuming power of the
fire, right? So anyway, that is the description of fire.
Okay, וממונך ושמירתן עליך, umamonecha ushmiratan alecha, and you're liable. הני נמי
כוח אחר מעורב בהן וממונך ושמירתן עליך. hanei nami koach acher me'urav
bahen umamonecha ushmiratan alecha. Same thing, you're going to call this אש,
esh, which it's certainly a חידוש to call this אש, esh, but
okay, but it'll have the same הלכות. Fine. אלא תולדותיהן כיוצא בהן,
ela toldoteihen keyotzei bahen, we've gone through this whole list, everything is
תולדה, same כיוצא בהן. וכי קאמר, vechi ka'amar, and I'm just going
to give you the one answer and we'll describe... we'll talk about
it tomorrow, וכי קאמר רב פפא אולדה דרגל. vechi ka'amar Rav Papa
atolada deregel. We're going to go back to רגל. So the גמרא
says, רגל? הא אוקימנא תולדה דרגל כרגל? ha okimna tolda deregel keregel?
We just... we said that that was the same. Ah, we were
hiding from you the fact in our back pocket... בחצי נזק צרורות.
bechatzi nezek tzerorot. How about when a רגל, an animal kicks pebbles?
Okay, and it's complete... now there you understand, by the way, why
you should be less liable and specifically by רגל. Since רגל is
effectively מתעסק, mit'asek, it's incidental and unintentional. So if I incidentally kick
a stone and the stone does something, that that stone is much
less me than if I throw a stone. Right, we've already brought
in the idea of כוח koach by an אדם. adam. If I
throw something at you, that's me. But let's say I didn't throw
it at you, I accidentally kicked a stone and that hit you.
Was that me hitting you? Right. So if the animal's צרורות tzerorot
of the animal's רגל, the... the כוח koach that comes through an
incidental act, that is a lot less like the animal itself. And
the הלכה halacha of that is you only pay half, you don't
pay full. Okay. So that is a תולדה שלא כיוצא בהן. tolada
shelo keyotzei bahen. A תולדה of רגל is, and by the way,
this is maybe similar to the תולדה of טומאה. tumah. Because it's
not a תולדה in the sense that it's a conceptually different category,
but it's one degree removed. Right? Just like remember the טומאה tumah
example? It's exactly רגל, the animal is walking, but it's one degree
removed from the animal walking because it's not the animal's leg that's
hitting something, it's the projectile that was kicked off by the animal's
leg that hit something. And the הלכה there is לאו כיוצא בהן,
lav keyotzei bahen, you only pay half. Okay. בחצי נזק צרורות כהלכתא
גמירי לה, bechatzi nezek tzerorot kehilchata gemiri lah, we have the tradition
דהלכתא
גמירי לה, dehilchata gemiri lah, that you pay half.
ואמאי קרי ליה תולדה דרגל? ve'amai kari leih tolada deregel? So what
makes it a רגל? Maybe it's its own category. So maybe it's
like קרן, keren, קרן keren you pay half. No, no, no, it's
not like... it's more like רגל, and what we're going to discuss
tomorrow, I'm not going to unpack what we just read, but we're
going to discuss tomorrow is why we still put it in the
רגל category and we see... rather than קרן, because קרן you also
pay half, but here conceptually it's רגל with a special הלכה of
לאו כיוצא בהן lav keyotzei bahen that you're only going to pay
half and not pay full.
Okay, we'll end here. דב, Dov, what's your question?
Yeah. Sorry, I just... I lost the piece. I thought the
גמרא.